<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vivat Rex A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on the day of his Maiesties happie inauguration, March 24⁰. 1614. And now newly published, by occasion of his late (no lesse happy) recovery. By John Rawlinson Dr of Divinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary.</title>
            <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115693</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850911</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850911</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1185:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vivat Rex A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on the day of his Maiesties happie inauguration, March 24⁰. 1614. And now newly published, by occasion of his late (no lesse happy) recovery. By John Rawlinson Dr of Divinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary.</title>
                  <author>Rawlinson, John, 1576-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield and Iames Short, printers to the famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, X, 14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:1"/>
            <p>VIVAT REX. <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLS CROSSE ON THE day of his Maieſties happie inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration, <hi>March</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>1614. And now newly publiſhed, by occaſion of His late (no leſſe happy) recovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN RAWLINSON D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Divinity, and one of his Maieſties Chaplaines in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vox populi, vox Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD.</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD and IAMES SHORT, Printers to the famous Vniverſitie. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY KING, JAMES by the grace of God, of <hi>Great Britanny, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defendor of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Moſt deare, and dread</hi> Soveraigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not long, ſince there was but a ſtep betwixt You and death, and that You were euen at the point of reſigning this your earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for that heauenly, whither your Queene of pretious memorie is lately gone before you to take poſſeſsion. The change though it had beene happie for You, yet needes muſt it haue beene bitter to vs that muſt haue loſt you. But bleſſed be God, who hath frustrated our feare by exchanging it for ioy. The wiſhed and thrice-welcome <hi>newes</hi> of your ioyfull <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and of the rolling away of the <hi>ſtone</hi> from the <hi>ſepulchre</hi> of Your <hi>bodie</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) hath alreadie been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at the <hi>Croſſe</hi> by a <hi>Right Reverend Praelate</hi> (a faithfull and timely meſſenger thereof) in the audience of all the States of your Kingdome.<note place="margin">The Lord B. of London.</note> This
<hi>VIVAT REX</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16148:3"/>of mine (proclaimed at the ſame <hi>Croſſe</hi> now fiue yeares ſince and vpward, on the day of your Maiesties moſt auſpicious and happie <hi>inveſtiture</hi> into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) is but the AMEN to that <hi>VIVIT REX</hi> of his. The reviving of Your Maieſtie is the reviving of this Sermon, and the reviuing of this Sermon wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (I doubt not) bee the reviving of many a good prayer for your Maieſtie. I am ſure, it was no ſooner vttered, but preſently the tongues of many your loyall Subiects beſpake it for the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> as deſirous to haue it alſo
<hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed</hi> in their hearts. Their hearts no leſſe fixed to ſay <hi>VIVAT REX,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob. Sat. l. 2. c. 4.</note> than was the tongue of the <hi>Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Crow</hi> docil to <hi>AVE CAESAR. Your Maieſtie</hi> (I dare ſay) will be farre from ſaying either to them, or me, as there <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſaith to the Crow; <hi>Satis domi ſalutatorum talium habeo;</hi> though if You ſhould, yet could neither of vs fitly reply with the Crow; <hi>Opera &amp; impenſa periit.</hi> For, whither ſuch our ſalutations bee accepted of <hi>You,</hi> or not, yet I haue learn'd of the Apoſtle, that they are <hi>accepted</hi> of God.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.3.</note> To <hi>You</hi> therfore (Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigne) doe we humbly offer this our ioint-ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>VIVAT REX:</hi> And for <hi>You</hi> doe we likewiſe offer vnto God this our ioint-ſupplication, <hi>VIVAT REX</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him againe and againe; long and long to prorogue the <hi>Terme</hi> of this your mortal life, to the vtmoſt extent of natures liueliehood; And when the date thereof ſhall expire, to immortalize
<hi>Your Life</hi> and <hi>Memorie, Your Crowne</hi> and <hi>Dignitie</hi> in the golden line of life, the line of <hi>Your</hi> Poſteritie. And, in the meane time, to grant, that as You are for birth <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16148:3"/>for glorie <hi>Eudoxus,</hi> for aequity <hi>Eunomius,</hi> for integritie
<hi>Eutropius,</hi> for pietie <hi>Euſebius,</hi> ſo for length of dayes you may be
<hi>Macrobius.</hi> Let him that is <hi>Amen it ſelfe</hi> ſay <hi>Amen!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Amen</hi> ſay I</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties</hi> moſt faithfull Subiect, and dutifull Seruant <hi>I. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>VIVAT REX.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16148:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.24.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VIVAT REX.</hi> Let the King liue. <hi>Or,</hi> God ſaue the King.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O ſooner haue I read my <hi>Text</hi> (Right Honorable,<note place="margin">PRAEFACE.</note> Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, &amp; beloued in the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate loue of God Chriſt Ieſus) but there are two things (I know) will ſeeme ſtrange vnto you. The <hi>one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An APOLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GY</note> that being to ſpeak vnto you <hi>two houres,</hi> I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to ſpeake but of <hi>two words:</hi> The <hi>other,</hi> that being to recognize and celebrate the happie
<hi>Inauguration</hi> of <hi>King Iames,</hi> I haue founded my diſcourſe vpon this
<hi>acclamation</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at the <hi>enthronizing</hi> of <hi>King Saul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 For the SHORTNES of the TEXT.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> though but <hi>two perſons,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate a world of men: So <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> though but <hi>two words,</hi> will beget a world of matter.</p>
            <p>Well may <hi>Rex,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> ſtand for <hi>Adam:</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> was
<hi>Rex mundi:</hi> the ſole King &amp; Monarch of the whole world: and aſwell may
<hi>Vivat</hi> goe for <hi>Eue.</hi> For <hi>Eue</hi> was <hi>Mater viventium,</hi> the Mother of the liuing:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.20.</note> euen as the <hi>Kings life</hi> is (as I may ſay) the <hi>Mother</hi> of all <hi>their liue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that liue vnder him.</p>
            <p>I haue compared <hi>Rex</hi> and <hi>Vivat,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Life,</hi> to
<hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife:</hi> And yet, in the proſecution, I ſhalbe faine to <hi>divorce them in words:</hi> But curſed be he,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16148:5"/>and let him periſh from off the face of the earth, who ſhall but haue the leaſt thought to <hi>divorce them in deede:</hi> to take the King from his life, or life from the King. They are <hi>vnited</hi> and bound together in Heauen in the <hi>bundle of life:</hi> Let no man then preſume to <hi>vnty</hi> or ſeparate them hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on earth. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 For the CHOICE.</note>Againe: I grounded n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y choice, not vpon any <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> or
<hi>ſymbolization</hi> of our <hi>Gratious Soueraigne</hi> with that <hi>vngratious Saul:</hi> as minding to make <hi>Saul</hi> either a <hi>precedent</hi> or a <hi>parallel</hi> to <hi>our King,</hi> who is as faire from <hi>Saul's</hi> vices, as was <hi>Saul</hi> from his virtues: But vpon the peoples chearefull, and ioyfull, and dutifull omination to King <hi>Saul:</hi> thereby the rather to excite and kindle the devotion of the people of <hi>Great Britanny</hi> to pray for the life of ſo good a King as <hi>King Iames,</hi> by the example of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo devoutly praying for the life of ſo bad a King as <hi>King Saul.</hi> And yet not to ſlander <hi>Saul</hi> (no more than I would the <hi>Divel</hi> himſelfe, who was <hi>Saul's Familiar</hi> in the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 28.) when at his entrance &amp; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re into the Kingdome, the people thus powred out their ſoules in devotion to God for him, he was then <hi>Tanquam muſtum,</hi> like
<hi>wine</hi> which purgeth and purifieth it ſelfe beſt while it is <hi>new:</hi> but ſoone after, he was turn'd <hi>In acetum,</hi> into vineger, which is <hi>vinum mortuum,</hi> dead wine: Inſomuch, that though he liued <hi>King</hi> in Iſrael 20 <hi>yeares,</hi> yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith he <hi>res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n'd</hi> but 2
<hi>yeares,</hi> 1 Sam. 13:<note place="margin">1 Sam 13.1. Stell. l. 2. de cont. mund. c. 31.</note> (18 of the 20 ſtood but for a cypher) becauſe (as <hi>Didacus Stella</hi> yields the reaſon)
<hi>Deus non numerat annos male expenſos, ſed ſolùm benè collocates:</hi> God in <hi>his Arithmetike</hi> reckons not thoſe yeares which we beſtow <hi>ill,</hi> but thoſe onely which we ſpend <hi>well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But take him at his verie beſt, and I hold him no fit <hi>mate</hi> or <hi>compiere</hi> for our King, who as farre ouer-toppes him in his <hi>virtues,</hi> as he did all the people in his
<hi>ſtature;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16148:5"/>— <hi>toto ſtans vertice ſuprà:</hi> being higher than any of them by the head &amp; ſhoulders: ver. 23: I will ſay more,<note place="margin">Verſe
23.</note> (and yet I will ſay no more than a truth) not onely <hi>Saul,</hi> but
<hi>Solomon</hi> himſelfe in all his royaltie, was not to hee compared to one of thoſe
<hi>Lilies</hi> that He beares in <hi>His Armes</hi> by our Saviours teſtimony,<note place="margin">Matt. 6.29.</note> Mat. 6. but much leſſe to one of thoſe <hi>Lilia virtutum</hi> (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeak's) thoſe li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies of his virtues that he beares in his breſt.<note place="margin">Bern. in Cant. Ser.
70.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divines diſtinguiſh <hi>Prayer</hi> into two ſorts: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">DIVISION.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Supplicatory,</hi> and
<hi>Gratulatory.</hi> The one, <hi>Pro beneficijs impetrandis:</hi> for benefits to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: The other <hi>Pro impetratis:</hi> for benefits already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
            <p>This ſhort ejaculation, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex,</hi> is both. It is both <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>ſupplicatory ſalutation,</hi>wherein the people zeal uſly pray vnto God for the preſervation and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manencie of <hi>Saul's reigne</hi> ouer them. And it's alſo
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>gratulatory acclamation,</hi> whereby the people te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify both their gladſomneſſe, and their thankfulneſſe vnto God for their King.</p>
            <p>Of both which while I ſhall ſpeake as briefly as I may, let me crave the continuance of your Honorable and Chriſtian attention. For (as our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, Ioh. 11.) <hi>Are there not twelue houres in the day?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.9.</note> or rather, are there not
8760 <hi>houres in the yeare?</hi> And will any then in this aſſembly ſhewe himſelfe ſo bad a Subiect, as to refuſe to render <hi>two</hi> of them backe to God, in a ſerious meditation and rememoration of <hi>this day's benefite?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> benefit, ſo greate, that (doubtleſſe) if our Sauiour Chriſt converſ'd againe vpon earth, and ſhould find but any one ſtanding idle in the mercat place now at the end of <hi>His Maieſties</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>yeare,</hi> as he found thoſe in the Goſpel at the
11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>houre:</hi> he would ſay vnto them,<note place="margin">Matt. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>Goe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16148:6"/>yee alſo into my vineyard,</hi> and there learne to bring forth the fruits of thankſgiuing for ſo rich a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And ſo farre would he be from rebuking vs, that ſay with them, Luke 19:<note place="margin">Luk. 19.38.</note> 
               <hi>Benedictus quivenit Rex in nomine Domini<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Bleſſed be the King that comes in the name of the Lord: that he would ſay to thoſe that ſhould mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, or be offeded at Vs,<note place="margin">Verſe. 40.</note> as ver. 40: <hi>I tell you, that if theſe ſhould hold their peace, the very ſtones would cry.</hi> In the Greeke, there is but one letters difference betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the people,</hi> and
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ſtone.</hi> And looke how eaſy it is for a man to alter <hi>that one letter:</hi> ſo, and much more eaſy is it for God, to change <hi>their whole nature.</hi> For God is able <hi>euen of ſtones to raiſe vp ſons vnto Abraham</hi> Luk. 3. If therefore the people ſhould ſo turne themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ſtones</hi> as not to cry:<note place="margin">Luk. 3.8.</note> then would God turne the ſtones into <hi>people,</hi> and they ſhould cry: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſaue the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take we it firſt as a <hi>ſupplication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">PART 1. SVPPLICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION. SVBDIVISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON.</note> and it ſtand's vpon two parts. The one, <hi>Perſonal:</hi> the other,
<hi>Real.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>Perſonal, Quis? who</hi> it is that is pray'd for? It is, <hi>Rex, the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Real, Quid? what</hi> it is that is pray'd for? It is, <hi>Vivat, that he may liue.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt there is <hi>Agniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> potentiae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his power and Soveraignty, as he is a
<hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond, there is <hi>Recognitio impotentiae:</hi> a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance or inſinuation of his weakenes and frailtie, as he is a <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as our bleſſed Saviour at his transfiguration took with him <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to mount <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abor,</hi> to giue them a raſte of his
<hi>glory,</hi> before he would ſpeake vnto them of mount <hi>Golgotha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe. 22.</note> the place of his <hi>mortality:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So let mee firſt thew you the <hi>King in his glory,</hi> out of this word <hi>Rex:</hi> and then <hi>in his frailty,</hi> out of this word, <hi>Vivat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16148:6"/>
               <hi>Phyſitians</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">WHO
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>X. Veſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 15. Alexan. Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> there is great difference betweene</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vena arterialis,</hi> and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arteria venalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is great difference (ſay the <hi>Naturaliſts</hi>) betweene</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iovis barba,</hi> and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barba Iovis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And great difference (ſay the <hi>Logicians</hi>) betweene theſe two propoſitions:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſte veſtitus eſt natui,</hi> and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atui eſt veſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, no leſſe difference is there betweene</p>
            <p> 
               <hi>Rex Vivat,</hi> Let the King liue, and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vivat Rex<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Let him liue a King.</p>
            <p>For, a King he may be, and yet not liue; the life of the wicked being not properly a life, but a death. And againe, Liue he may, and yet not liue a King; the dutie of a King being the better halfe of a King. For a King is called <hi>Rex, a regendo,</hi> of ruling:<note place="margin">SVB<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>IVISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON. THE VERY N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a King
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>phes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ON<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>Y; which ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ruling (yee know) includes aſwel a <hi>dutie,</hi> as a <hi>dignitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore of the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>Kingly dignity,</hi> &amp; then of the
<hi>exigence</hi> of <hi>Kingly duty.</hi> The one is <hi>Praeeſſe,</hi> to rule, not to be ruled by others: There's the honor of his place: The other is <hi>Prodeſſe,</hi> to rule for the good and benefit of others: There's the teno of his office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex.</hi> Let him liue a King.</p>
            <p>And a King what is he, but that maine <hi>Ocean</hi> from whence all the <hi>leſſer ſtreames</hi> of <hi>Nobility,</hi> of <hi>Gentry,</hi> of <hi>authority</hi> are derived? The excellency of whoſe <hi>dignity</hi> ſhines firſt of all in the <hi>Author</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reator</hi> of it,<note place="margin">1 In the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>HOR.</note> 
               <hi>GOD</hi> himſelfe: For S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> calls it
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the creature of God: 1 Pet. 2: as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calls it
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ordinance of God: Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13. <hi>Per me Reges regnant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Prov
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> By me Kings reigne; (ſaith God in the perſon of wiſdome, Pro. 8.)
<hi>Per me,</hi> not <hi>Perſe:</hi> They reigne by my appointment, not by any power or virtue of their owne. Their <hi>Super</hi> is but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16148:7"/>
               <hi>Deſuper:</hi> Their being aboue other men, it is from God aboue, to whoſe
<hi>Supremacy</hi> all Superiority muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. For <hi>Excelſo excelſior alius eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5.7.</note> as it is Eccleſiaſtes 5: God the moſt High who dwelleth in the higheſt heauens, is higher than the higheſt Princes Highneſſe heere on earth.<note place="margin">Prou. 21.1.</note> As <hi>Cor Regis,</hi> the heart of the King is <hi>in the hand of God:</hi> Prov. 21: So is alſo <hi>Corona Regis,</hi> the Crowne of the King:<note place="margin">Dan. 4.14.</note> and (that al the world may know it ſo to be) it's fronted with a
<hi>Noverint vniverſi</hi> Dan 4: that <hi>the moſt High hath power ouer the kingdome of men, and giue's it to whomſoeuer he will.</hi> Yea not onely <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert,</hi> but <hi>Transfert</hi> too: he not onely <hi>collate's,</hi> but <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late's</hi> kingdomes at his pleaſure: For
<hi>becauſe of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing, and wrongs, and riches gotten by decerte, the kingdome is tranſlated from one people to another:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus: 10.8.</note> Eccl. 10.</p>
            <p>God then being the Author of Imperiall, or Princely dignity,<note place="margin">1 Pet.
2.17.</note> no merveile, if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> 1 Pet. 2: haue as it were pared and coupled theſe two together in one yoake: <hi>Feare God, Honor the King:</hi> becauſe if yee doe the one, ye will doe the other. If ye feare God, who is <hi>Proto-rex,</hi> the Supreme, or Prime King, then ye will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor his <hi>Pro-rex,</hi> or vnder-king whom himſelfe hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2ly In the TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENDENT POWER.</note>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>: The excellencie of
<hi>Kingly dignity</hi> ſhines in the <hi>tranſcendent power</hi> and <hi>praerogatiue</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> which is ſuch: that <hi>Plus poteſt rex, quam vnli bonus rex:</hi> A king in his abſolute and vnlimited power is able to do more than a good King will doe.</p>
            <p>It was therefore good advice which <hi>Agapetus</hi> gaue the Emperour
<hi>Inſtinian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. You ſhall doe well (ſaith he) to impoſe vpon your ſelfe a neceſſity of keeping the lawes as hauing no ſuperior here on earth, that may compell you to keepe them. You ſhall do the law great honor in keeping it: and ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16148:7"/>ſtrike into your ſubiects a ſcare of tranſgreſſing it.</p>
            <p>A King then though he be free from <hi>coaction</hi> to keepe the law yet muſt he voluntarily ſubmit his will to the <hi>direction</hi> of the law: the difference betweene a <hi>good King</hi> and a <hi>tyrant</hi> being but this; that a <hi>King</hi> makes the law his will, becauſe he will's, that which the law will's: But a <hi>tyrant</hi> makes his will a law, becauſe what he will's, he will haue to be law.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Antigonus,</hi> King of <hi>Macedony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cael Rhod. l. 23. c.
14.</note> when one of his Sycophants told him, that in a King all things are iuſt and honeſt: yea but (ſaith he) none but barbarous Kings are of that opinion. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For mine owne part (ſaith he) I thinke onely thoſe things honeſt that are honeſt indeed, onely thoſe things iuſt that are iuſt indeed.</p>
            <p>And it was but a mocke that <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> gaue to King <hi>Alexander,</hi> when ſeeing the <hi>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture of Iuſtice</hi> iet cheeke by iowle on the right ſide of <hi>Iupiter's image:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch. ad punc. indoct.</note> hee told him, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was not thereby bound to doe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; but that the people were thereby bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that whatſoeuer <hi>Iupiter</hi> did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lawfull and iuſt. For a good King wilbe ſo farre from thinking it lawfull for him to breake the law, that hee will be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a keeper of the law: a keeper of it in both ſignifications of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: He will not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <hi>Serv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> but <hi>Obſervare:</hi> not
<hi>preſerue</hi> it onely, but <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue</hi> it too: that is, he will neither violate it himſelfe, nor yet ſuffer it to ſuffer violence of others; and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call'd by
<hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>zer,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>liuing law:</hi> by <hi>Xenophon</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>ſeeing law:</hi> by the <hi>Roman Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Lex
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oquens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> a <hi>speaking law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe him to be the very worſt that may be, a tyrant: one that will make the law an out-law; yet ſhall it not be lawfull for any mortall man vindictiuely to meddle with him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16148:8"/>
               <hi>David</hi> though he were a King, &amp; had therefore more right than any inferior perſon to take vengeance of King <hi>Saul</hi> who contrary to all law ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uity. &amp; religion, had cauſleſly ſlaine the
<hi>Prieſts</hi> of the Lord: 1. Sam. 24. yet it's ſaid, that <hi>his heart ſmote him,</hi> becauſe he had but <hi>cut of the lap of Saul's garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam.
24.6.</note> who was the <hi>annointed</hi> of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Marke that, thou that boaſteſt thy ſelfe to bee <hi>Peters Succeſſor</hi> and herein indeed exceedeſt him, that, as <hi>Peter</hi> cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his care,<note place="margin">Hieronym. epiſt. l. 3. ep. 3.</note> which by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ierom's</hi> interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a <hi>King:</hi> So thou by thy diueliſh agents &amp; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cutt'ſt off not only an
<hi>eare,</hi> or a <hi>lap of the garments</hi> of thoſe Kings that will not ſtoope to thy lure, but their <hi>crownes,</hi> and their <hi>heads</hi> too.</p>
            <p>Surely, thou hadſt never any ſuch warrant from God, who was ſo far from giuing any commiſſion either to <hi>David</hi> or any other, to put <hi>Saul</hi> (though a wicked
<hi>King</hi>) to the ſword as that he ſuffer'd <hi>Saul</hi> to fall vpon his own ſword,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 31.4.</note> and ſo to be his owne executioner: 1. Sam. 31. as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no earthly hand had beene fit to execute
<hi>Saul</hi> (a <hi>King</hi>) but his owne.</p>
            <p>A faire example and warning-piece for Princes, to teach them <hi>Sibi imperare,</hi> to be Kings over themſelues, leaſt God ſuffer them <hi>Sibi poeuas irrogare,</hi> to be avenged of themſelues.</p>
            <p>It was the ſaying of that heathen <hi>Marcellus</hi> in <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. l. 4. pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo poſt init.</note> that he would <hi>Bonos imperatores voto expetere, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, tole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are:</hi> pray for Emperors, if they were good, but patiently endure them, though they were never ſo bad.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeeme by him, that <hi>heathen Rome</hi> was not then ſo heatheniſh as now it is. For is it not now the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (and doe they not alſo countenance their doctrine by their practiſed) that kings if they be bad are not
<hi>Tolerandi,</hi> to be tolerated with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16148:8"/>but <hi>emedis to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lendi,</hi> to be rid out of the way by violence? nay, be they otherwiſe never ſo good, (if not good for their turne) that they are no <hi>voto expetends,</hi> to be deſired of God by prayer, but
<hi>Glad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o impetends,</hi> to be diſpatched of men by the ſword?</p>
            <p>But was this either the doctrine, or the practiſe of the Primitiue Church? Surely, no.<note place="margin">Per. Martyr. in Sarn. 24.</note> For when thoſe more than tyrannica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l tyrants to ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly perſecuted and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Chriſtians with moſt exquiſite tortures &amp; tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet neither <hi>Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> did once offer to arme, or incenſe the people againſt them Nay, they rather admoniſht them, to make their ſupplications vnto God for them and namely for <hi>Nero</hi> that bloudy perſecutor, whom therefore S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, call's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Lyon,</hi> 2. Tim. 4.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.17. 3 In the FAC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Gerſon.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of <hi>Princely dignity</hi> ſhines in the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry face</hi> and
<hi>countenance</hi> of a King. For there is <hi>Character tremendus in vultibus Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> An impreſſion or character of dreadfull Maieſtie ſtamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the very viſage of a King. The Lyon's looke is terrible to all the beaſts of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And <hi>Nature</hi> herſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfe (ſaith that <hi>Chiefe Secretary</hi> of Nature) hath made the <hi>Phyſiognomy</hi> of Princes to bee ſuch,<note place="margin">Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot.</note> as ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an lawfull feare and reverence into as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as behold them; euen as it is ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod 34:<note place="margin">Exod.
34.30.</note> that after <hi>his conference with God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the skin of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> face ſhone ſo bright, that the people were afraid to come neare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> And laſtly the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of
<hi>Kingly dignity</hi> ſhines in the very <hi>appellations</hi> of <hi>1 King;</hi> that he is called a <hi>Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. In the AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ATIONS.</note> a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>God.</hi> I will but onely ſalute them in a word.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt he is called a <hi>Head,</hi> Eſay 9: and 1 Sam. 15:<note place="margin">1 HEAD. Eſa. 9.14 1. Sam. 15.17.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as the <hi>Head</hi> is the Prince of the Naturall body; ſo the <hi>Prince</hi> is the Head of the Politike body; being to it as is the head to the reſt of the members, the fountaine both of ſenſe, and motion. And therefore as in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16148:9"/>body, ſo is it in the <hi>Body politike:</hi> If the body be without a head, it preſently fall's to the ground, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth: or of the head bee ill affected, the whole body i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by and by diſabled. Whence it is, that
<hi>Caput,</hi> as it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a <hi>head,</hi> ſo it alſo ſignifieth <hi>life</hi> becauſe <hi>Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> capits: caput eſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alutis:</hi> the ſafety of the head is the head of the bodies ſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 A SHEP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEARD. Ariſt. Eth. l. 8. c 11.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 44.28.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lex. Philo.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, A King is called
<hi>Paſtor,</hi> the ſhepheard of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. A man
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by God himſelfe to <hi>King Cyrus,</hi> 100 yeares ere he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> borne: Fſo:
44. So do <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> and <hi>Philo Inau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vſually compare a King to a <hi>Shephea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> and the people to <hi>ſheepe:</hi> becauſe as ſheepe will runn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thorow a gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which the firſt haht broken, though it bee to the very endangering of then liues: ſo the rage of the people ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gthened by error and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their nature, is ſuch, that vnleſſe they haue a King to recall and guide them, it's a venture but they run deſperately to their owne ruine.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3 FATHER Ariſt. l. 8. Eth. c. 10.</note>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> A King is called
<hi>Pater,</hi> a Father: be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe (ſaith <hi>Ariſt</hi>) he muſt exerciſe
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the authority of a <hi>Father,</hi> not of a <hi>Maſter,</hi> over his Subiect. This did <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> (an heathen Emperour) ſee by the dim &amp; glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring light of Nature: of whom <hi>Macrobius</hi> write's, that hee carried ſuch an entire and fatherly affection to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob. Sat. l. 2. c.
5.</note> that he call'd it <hi>Filiam ſuam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> his owne daughter: and therefore refuſed to bee call'd <hi>Dominus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Lord or Maiſter of his countrey, and would onely be call'd <hi>Pater Patria,</hi> the father of his countrey: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he govern'd it <hi>Non per timorem, ſed per amorem:</hi> not by feare, but by loue. A title which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pope's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity</hi> for theſe many ſucceſſions hath much affected, though litle deſerved. For the <hi>Pope</hi> by his very name <hi>(Papa)</hi> would haue vs to vnderſtand, that hee is <hi>Pa: pa:</hi> that is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Pater Patriae:</hi> the Father of <hi>his Countrey,</hi> which (by his interpretation) is <hi>all the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16148:9"/>But let him be what he is; I am ſure, that (as <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſaith in
<hi>Xenophon</hi>) there is no oddes at all,<note place="margin">Xe ph. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 8. ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. 12.</note> betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good King, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good father. And therefore hath God ioyn'd a King and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it were in the ſame <hi>patent</hi> of honor: nor is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t that directly enioyn's vs to <hi>honor the King,</hi> ſaue onely that which binde's vs to <hi>honor our parents,</hi> which is the <hi>fift commandement:</hi> &amp; it's therefore placed <hi>In meditullio</hi> in the very midſt betweene the <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond table,</hi> to ſhew, that the King ought to be (<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos vtriuſque tabulae</hi> the preſeruer of both tables of the Law: that he muſt haue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his right hand the <hi>firſt table,</hi> which is of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religious duties</hi> towards God: and in his left hand the <hi>ſecond table,</hi> which is of <hi>Policy and Ciuil duties</hi> towards men; that ſo there may be aſwel <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erna profeſſio doctrinae,</hi> an outward profeſſion of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gubernatio externa diſciplinae,</hi> the government of outward diſcipline. For wee are not to imagine that a King is but
<hi>Armentarius,</hi> a heardſman onely, that he ſhould haue care but of the bodies of his people. No: a King is <hi>Mixta perſona cum Sacerdote,</hi> a mixt perſon with a Prieſt, hauing alſo the procuration and care of <hi>Gods Worſhip,</hi> and ſo conſequently of the
<hi>Soules of men.</hi> And therefore doth God promiſe it as a ſpeciall bleſſing to his Church, Eſay 49. that <hi>Kings ſhall be Nutriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa 49.23. P. 82.6.</note> her nurſing Fathers, and
<hi>Queenes, Nutrices,</hi> her nurſing Mothers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. GOD.</note>Fourthly and laſtly: a King is call'd <hi>Deus,</hi> a
<hi>God,</hi> Pſal. 82: Yet <hi>Non per naturam, ſed participative:</hi> a God (ſaith
<hi>Aquinas</hi>) not by nature,<note place="margin">Aq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. in Po e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. phil.</note> but by participation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his power from God, as <hi>the powers that are, are ordein'd of God,</hi> Rom. 13: and <hi>Aſſimilative,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om 13.1. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Apoll. hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gl</note> a God by ſimilitude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or likeneſſe: As hauing like God himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, power both of life and death. For hee can <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vificare &amp; occidere,</hi> quicken, and kill men at pleaſure:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16148:10"/>He can breath into the face of man (his ciuil creature) the breath both of life and death: He can raiſe men out of the duſt, and ſet them even with the Pieres and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his people. Yea, what God doth of himſelfe, that doth the King by others. God of himſelfe knowes all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings: So doth a King by his
<hi>Intelligencers.</hi> God of himſelfe can do all things: So can a King by his
<hi>Officers.</hi> God is in all places at once by himſelfe: So is a <hi>King</hi> by his
<hi>Deputies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now,<note place="margin">2 DVTY. Marc. 15.26.</note> becauſe all theſe excellent titles of
<hi>dignity</hi> will be no better to a King than was Chriſts title of <hi>Rex Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum,</hi> the King of the Iews, to him; that is, but titles of his further condemnation, vnleſſe he be as ſtudiouſly iealous of his <hi>duty,</hi> as of his <hi>dignity</hi> (for not the hauing, but the deſerving of honour, is it that makes a King tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honorable,<note place="margin">Xenoph.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> l. 1.</note> as being (ſaith <hi>Xenophon</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſuperexcellent worke:) It muſt therefore be the prime care of a King, not ſo much to ſtudy how hee may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Great King;</hi> (which (ſaith <hi>Suidas</hi>) was the title proper to the <hi>Perſian King:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suid. in voc. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kings hauing only the <hi>additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their peoples names</hi> giuen vnto them, as King of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> or <hi>the like:</hi>) as how he may deſcrue the title of <hi>Optimus,</hi> which <hi>Pliny</hi> giues to the Emperor <hi>Traian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. Panepyr. Traian. p. 81.</note> the title of the Beſt, which indeed is the beſt title: That, as he is beſt by virtue of his place, ſo he may be likewiſe beſt by place of his vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; that is, that he ioine his <hi>duty</hi> with his
<hi>dignity:</hi> which is the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing I noted in this word <hi>Rex,</hi> or King.</p>
            <p>Of which a word, and away; becauſe the <hi>duty</hi> is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably vnited to the titles of <hi>dignity,</hi> that forget the one he cannot, but he muſt alſo neceſſarily make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrecke of the other.</p>
            <p>For as there is a duty which Subiects owe to their King: ſo is there alſo a duty which the King owes to his Subiects. The duty which Subiects owe to their King is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16148:10"/>
               <hi>obedience;</hi> and that is <hi>Summum dominationis bonum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gerſon.</note> the chiefe happineſſe of a King. The duty which the King owes to his Subiects is <hi>loue;</hi> and that is <hi>ſummum ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis bonum:</hi> the chiefe happineſſe of the Subiects.</p>
            <p>As S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> bids, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.3</note> 
               <hi>Honor wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows that are widows indeed:</hi> 1 Tim. 5. So are thoſe Kings indeed to be honor'd that are
<hi>Kings indeed.</hi> And that which makes them <hi>Kings indeed,</hi> is not their bare and empty names of dignity, vnleſſe they be alſo accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a faithfull diſcharge of their dutie. A thing not vnknowne of old to their very children playing in the ſtreets, who in their ſport which <hi>Iulius Pollux</hi> call's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Alciat in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigat. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Tacit. Iul. Pollux.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 9. c. 7. Horat. ep. l. 1. ep. 1.</note> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a King, becauſe in it they were wont to chooſe a—King. <hi>Rex eris, aiunt, Sirecte facias</hi>—, Do well (ſay they) &amp; you ſhall be a King: wheras a King, if he haue nought but the <hi>name</hi> of a King to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend him, he ſhall be no better than <hi>Rex larvatus, a King on a the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre;</hi> or <hi>Rex ludicer, a King at cheſſe, a wooden King.</hi> Let the King faile but in <hi>his</hi> duty, &amp; the people will not faile to faile in
<hi>theirs.</hi> The Poets feigne that <hi>Venus</hi> had a little ſonne, which ſhe call'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Niph. l. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</note> which could never come to any growth or ſtature, till ſhee had brought forth another ſon, which was call'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as if you would ſay, <hi>Loue for loue.</hi> Like her ſonne
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the loue of the ſubiects to their King. Like her ſonne
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the loue of the King to his ſubiects. The Moral is; there muſt be an enter courſe of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> betweene the <hi>King</hi> &amp; his
<hi>Subiects.</hi> For if the King reguard not his Subiects, as Subiects; no more will the Subiects reguard the King, as a King: which made that good Emperor <hi>Traian</hi> profeſſe; <hi>Se velle eſſe talem ſubditis ſuis, qualem vellet dominum, ſuum ſibi fore, ſi ſubijceretur:</hi> that he would be none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe affected to his Subiects, than hee would wiſh the <hi>Emperor</hi> ſhould be to him, if himſelfe were a Subiect.<note place="margin">TO KEEPE his people.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now a King ſhall beſt expreſſe his loue and duty to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16148:11"/>his Subiects, if he keepe them in <hi>tranquillity,</hi> in
<hi>ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in <hi>ſecurity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in <hi>tranquillity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 In <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>anquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>affliction</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion</hi> is the ſcope of tyranny: ſo is
<hi>peace</hi> the end and vpſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of al good government. For a <hi>King</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the throne of iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>chaſeth away all evill with his eyes. All evill?</hi> what's tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith that <hi>Pax eſt omne bonum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin. in Pſal. 127.</note> Peace is all good: and therefore <hi>A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie,</hi> diſſenſion and diviſion is <hi>all evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then there ſhalbe diſſenſions and heart-burnings among the people, it's the braine and wiſdome of the King that muſt compoſe them; like as <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> notes, that the cold moiſtneſſe of the braine is it that makes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ariſt. de part. mund. 2. c. 7.</note> that cooles and qualifies the overboyling heat of the heart: and that therefore needfull it is, that <hi>whatſoever creature hath a heart, ſhould alſo haue a head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So doth the great king <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> otherwiſe call'd <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> in his epiſtle which he wrote to the Princes of 127 Provinces, profeſſe, that <hi>he would not abuſe his power, but with aequity and gentleneſſe would he governe his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſet them in a peaceable life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter. 13.2.</note> Eſter, 13.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there is not a more Princely, or royall virtue than <hi>Peace,</hi> therefore is
<hi>Chriſt</hi> call'd <hi>Princeps pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> the Prince of peace,<note place="margin">Eſa.
9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Eſa. 9.</p>
            <p>And our manner is to giue Kings as a <hi>speciall title,</hi> the title of <hi>Serexiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is,</hi> or <hi>Paciſici: moſt Peaceable,</hi> or
<hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly A King muſt keepe his people in
<hi>ſufficiency.</hi> For,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. In <hi>ſufficien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi>
               </note> for a King to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ome and cate vp his ſubiects by exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is a thing no leſte vnnaturall, than for a man to eate the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh of his owne aimes. Should the head in the naturall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y draw all the bloud, and marrow, and ſubſtance of the other members to it ſelfe, it muſt needs turne to the deſtruction of the head it ſelfe. For how ſhould the head continue without a body? Or how
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16148:11"/>ſhould the body but pine &amp; periſh without ſuſteinance? What men? No
<hi>Subſidies</hi> at all to be levied<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yes: Reaſon good the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple ſhould yield
<hi>Subſidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ayde or aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the King who is <hi>Praeſidium,</hi> the ſtay and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the people?</p>
            <p>I only wiſh with Reverend <hi>Gerſon</hi> that <hi>two Cautions</hi> may be carefully needed.<note place="margin">Gerſon.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>One;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 1 Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>louy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g</hi> of <hi>Subſidies.</hi> Cic. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1.</note> That Subſidies be levied <hi>In bond aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; aequalitate,</hi> with good aequity and aequality tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-out the whole body of the kingdome. The <hi>Orator</hi> giue's the reaſon out of <hi>Plato,</hi> becauſe
<hi>Particiuium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere partem ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligere;</hi> To lay a heavier loade vpon one part of the people than vpon anot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, is to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Common wealth a thing no leſſe pernicious and capital, than is <hi>Sedition. Let the bigger horſe</hi> (ſaith the Proverb)
<hi>beare the greater burden.</hi> But let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either leſſe, nor bigger beare a greater, than they are able. O how bleſſed are the people (and yet ſo bleſſed haue wee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto bene) whoſe Kings are like thoſe
<hi>holy</hi> and <hi>aquiate beaſts,</hi> of whome it is ſaid, that <hi>Manus ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nis ſub
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 1.8.</note> the hands of a man came out from vnder then wings! that is, vnder the protection of whoſe wings poore <hi>Artificers</hi> and <hi>handiecrafts</hi> liue in peace, not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd or bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den'd with exactions! And (that they may be the leſſe burden'd) becauſe it many times fall's out, that it is not the <hi>Idol Bel</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Prieſts</hi> that eate vp all,<note place="margin">Dan. 14.13.</note> and that, in the night: that is not <hi>Kings</hi> themſelues, but then <hi>Seruants</hi> and
<hi>Officers</hi> that devoure all in ſecret; (theſe by conveyances vnder hand, as thoſe by convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances vnder ground:) therefore as God though hee hath mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kings his Deputies yet his eyes are alwayes on them to ſee what they do: So m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Kings eyes bee ſometimes on their vnder-officers to obſerue what they do.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>giuing of gifts.</hi>
               </note>2 His <hi>Other Caution is;</hi> That <hi>thouſands</hi> are not to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16148:12"/>impoveriſhed, that ſome <hi>few</hi> may be enriched; <hi>Ne libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitas crudelis ſit largitas:</hi> leſt in ſuch caſe (ſaith hee) Princely liberality proue to bee no better than bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cruelty.</p>
            <p>This duty of mainteining the people in <hi>Sufficiency</hi> ſtand's Princes vpon ſomuch the rather, becauſe they are <hi>Villice, God's Stewards:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.2.</note> and being therefore one day <hi>to giue an account of their Stewardſhip,</hi> that is, of the goods of the Common-wealth, not as <hi>Lords,</hi> but as <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> they muſt ſee that they ſo ceuen their reckonings, as that they may bee found <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illici aquitatis, righteous Stewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly,<note place="margin">3 In <hi>Security.</hi>
               </note> A King muſt keepe his people in <hi>Security.</hi> For, as to the people the Kings ſafety muſt be the <hi>Supreme Law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s populi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prema lex eſto. <hi>Eſay 14.14.</hi>
               </note> So to a King the peoples ſafety.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Lucifer's</hi> ſin, that he would be <hi>ſimilis Altiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> like God himſelfe: which ſome Divines thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound; that he would rule as Lord ouer all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>ſine vllâ obligatione ad earum cuſtodiam ſeu ſerviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> without any obligation, or ty of duty in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, or ſervice: whereas contrarywiſe, hee ought to haue knowne, <hi>that ſervitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eó maior eſt, quo maior domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio:</hi> the more ſoueraignty, the more ſervice. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Menander</hi> an old Greeke Poët ſaid,<note place="margin">Menand.</note> that
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The onely Seruant in a family is the Maſter of the family.</hi> So that, to be a King is but <hi>Nobile ſervitium,</hi> a noble kinde of ſervice;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th the people can not be ſecure but by his care; and his owne pillow muſt he ſtuffe with <hi>thiſtles</hi> that he may ſtuffe the pillowes of his people with <hi>downe.</hi> A thing not obſcurely ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our bleſſed Saviour, who was neuer ſo vexed and tormented in all his life-time, as when hee ware the roabes and enſignes of a King,<note place="margin">Marke 15.17.</note> Marke. 15: when in a mockage they
<hi>clad him with purple,</hi> and <hi>crowned him with thornes, and put a ſcepter of reede into his hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16148:12"/>Such then being the cares &amp; vexations that are wont to attend vpon Kings, the leſſe wonder is it, if in that ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigmatical parable propounded by <hi>Iotham,</hi> Iudg.
9:<note place="margin">Iudg 9.8.</note> where the trees went forth to anoint a King ouer them; the
<hi>Oliue</hi> would not leaue his fatneſſe to macerate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the cares of a kingdome: nor the <hi>Fig-tree</hi> his ſweetneſſe, to taſte of the bitter-ſweets of a kingdome: not the <hi>Vine</hi> his fruitfulneſſe, chearing both God and man, to afflict himſelfe with the barren cares of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Onely <hi>Rhamnus,</hi> the ſcratching and goaring &amp; barren bramble, good for nothing but to make fewel for the ſire, he ſtep's out, and profer's his ſervice.<note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> It yee will indeede (ſaith he) annoint me King ouer you, <hi>Sub v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nbrâ meâ requieſcite:</hi> Come, and put your truſt vnder my ſhadow. So that, hee is worſe than a <hi>bramble-King,</hi> that will refuſe to ſhade and ſhelter his people from the ſcorching heate of violence and wrongs.</p>
            <p>It was an honorable title which was giuen to good King <hi>Dauid</hi> 1 Sam. 22:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.2.</note> (which is alſo euen haereditary to our King,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as deſcending vnto him from his worthy
<hi>Grandfather</hi>) that he was the <hi>Poore man's King:</hi> For there gathered vnto him (ſaith the text) <hi>all men that were in trouble, and all men that were in debt, and all thoſe that were vexed in minde, and he was their Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, how ſhould a King gaine this Title to himſelfe but by protecting &amp; ſecuring his people? or how ſhould he better ſecure them, than by returning for <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> Let the King liue; <hi>Currat lex,</hi> Let the Law haue his forth: that is, for their prayer for his ſafetie, a warrant for their ſafety: Not diſarming &amp; taming his Laws, as
<hi>Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> (in <hi>Lampridius</hi>) did his Lyons &amp; Leopards:<note place="margin">I amprid. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al.</note> vſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely <hi>Ad terrorem &amp; delectamentum:</hi> to affright others, and delight himſelfe: but <hi>executing rigteous iuſtice and iudgement,</hi> the true end why Princes are advanced to the throne: 2 Chron. 9:<note place="margin">2 Chron. 9.8.</note> as that bleſſed <hi>Queene Eliſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16148:13"/>proteſted of herſelfe in a ſpeach to her Lords, that <hi>her verdict went euer with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he truth of her knowledge.</hi> For
<hi>Iuſtice</hi> (ſaith that Great <hi>Moraliſt</hi>)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or perfection of the Law:<note place="margin">Plutarch. ad princ. indoct.</note> the Law is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the worke of the Prince: the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Image of GOD digeſting and ordering all things. As if he ſhould ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that a Prince is then indeede the Image of God, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> carefull to make good Lawes, &amp; no leſſe careful to execute them, that his people liuing vnder him in ſecurity and ſafety, may haue iuſt cauſe to pray for his ſafety; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo from the <hi>Perſonal</hi> part of the Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lication, which is <hi>Rex,</hi> the King;<note place="margin">2 VIV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>T.</note> I come now to the <hi>Real,</hi> which is <hi>Vivat Let him liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vivat Let him liue,</hi> or, (as all our Engliſh tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reade it) <hi>God ſaue him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> things.</note> And ſo in this one word <hi>Vivat</hi> there are two things implied. The one is
<hi>Dator</hi> the giuer of life, (<hi>God</hi> himſelfe) to whom the Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is directed: The other, <hi>Donum,</hi> the gift of life, for which the Supplication is commenced.<note place="margin">1 DATOR. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 75.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt then of the <hi>Giuer:</hi> As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion,</hi> Pſal. 75: ſo may we of <hi>Saluation;</hi> It <hi>comes nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South:</hi> we may add; no, nor yet from the <hi>North;</hi> but from <hi>God alone</hi> who ſett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s vp. &amp; pull's downe: who ſaue's, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy's at pleaſure. Kings are wont <hi>Occidere ſuper aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt.</hi> to ſet in the Eaſt: that is, to fall when they are in their aſcendent, or elſe at the very top of their aſcent:<note place="margin">Pſal. 67.4. Act. 17.25. Theocoret. epit. dium. decret. l. 5.</note> But it's God onely that doth <hi>Aſcendere ſuper occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſum:</hi> triumph ouer death it ſelfe, Pſal
67: He it is that giue's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Life and breath,</hi> Act 17: and (as
<hi>Theodoret</hi> ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>om. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, decret.</hi>) doth not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>giue life,</hi> but
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſaue life.</hi> And not the life o <hi>beaſts</hi> onely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.6.</note> but of <hi>men</hi> too; <hi>Thou Lord doſt ſaue both man and beaſt,</hi> Pſal. 36. And not of <hi>inferiour men</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16148:13"/>onely, but of <hi>Kings</hi> too: For <hi>Ipſe eſt,</hi> it's <hi>He,</hi> (and <hi>onely He</hi>) <hi>that giue's deliuerance vnto Kings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
144.10</note> Pſal. 144: As on the other ſide, it's <hi>He</hi> that doth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>indemiare ſpiritus principum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.12.</note> Pſal. 76: <hi>diſcard Kings &amp; Queenes out of the ſtocke when pleaſeth him:</hi> or, (as the <hi>Metaphor</hi> imports)
<hi>tuck</hi> &amp; <hi>take away</hi> the Spirits of Princes, as a man would <hi>tuck grapes.</hi> And he is ſaid to tuck them as grapes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as grapes, they exhilarate the hearts of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fallax equus ad ſalutem; A horſe</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>David</hi>) <hi>is but a vaine thing to ſaue a man:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.17.</note> Pſal. 33: And <hi>Vana ſalus hominis; as vaine is the helpe of man,</hi> ſaith the ſame <hi>Dauid:</hi> Pſal. 60. that is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 60.11.</note> the people can no more ſaue a King, than can a horſe. All that they can doe, is but onely <hi>ſalutare,</hi> to wiſh and pray for his health, (as here they do:) It's God onely that can <hi>ſoluare,</hi> giue him health, and helpe him in the time of trouble. God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that hath life for his owne <hi>free-hold,</hi> and can therefore ſay <hi>Aſſertive,</hi> by way of <hi>oath, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivo ego, dicit Dominus, As I liue (ſaith the Lord)</hi> Ier. 22:<note place="margin">Ier. 22.24.</note> Kings themſelues hold their liues but <hi>In Capite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in chiefe, as from him; and can therfore ſay but
<hi>Optative,</hi> by way of wiſh, or of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that which here the people ſay;
<hi>Vivat.</hi> Some Kings haue by their Subiects beene entitled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Sauiours:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyr.</note> but God is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Sauiour of theſe Sauiours.</hi> That's the firſt thing I noted in this word <hi>Vivat,</hi> God ſaue him; that God is <hi>Dator,</hi> the Author &amp; giuer of life.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond is <hi>Donum,</hi> the gift it ſelfe; or thing pray'd for, which is
<hi>Life. Vivat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 DON<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>M. A foure-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old LIFE. 1 CORI O RAI. 2 POLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>KE. 3 SPIRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVAL. 4 AETER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAL.</note> Let him liue.</p>
            <p>Take we the word <hi>Vivat</hi> in it's full latitude, and it's a prayer vnto God that he would bleſſe the King not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a <hi>corporal</hi> or <hi>temporal life.</hi> which conſiſteth in the coniunction of ſoule and body, but alſo with <hi>other three liues:</hi> A <hi>Politike,</hi> or <hi>Ciuil life,</hi> which conſiſteth in the vnity of the King and his Subiects in one Law. A <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>gratious life:</hi> and An <hi>Aeternal,</hi> or
<hi>glorious
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16148:14"/>life;</hi> which two laſt liues conſiſt in the mutuall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of amity betweene God and the ſoule; though the former but <hi>Inchoatè,</hi> imperfitly here in this world: the later
<hi>Completè<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> perfitly in the world to come.</p>
            <p>The Poët (<hi>Aencïd, l.</hi> 8.) hath a fiction of <hi>King Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Aen. l. 8.</note> that he had <hi>three ſoules,</hi> and conſequently <hi>three liues:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Naſcenticui tres animas Feronia mater</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Horrendum dictu) dederat, terna arma movenda,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ter letho ſteruendus erat.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>But, I am ſure, it's no fiction, but an vndoubted truth, that euery good &amp; Chriſtian King hath not onely <hi>three liues</hi> in poſſeſſion, but alſo a <hi>fourth</hi> in reverſion. The three <hi>in poſſeſſion,</hi> are his <hi>Natural,</hi> his
<hi>Ciuil,</hi> and his <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual life:</hi> and the <hi>fourth in reverſion,</hi> is
<hi>Eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>life of Nature,</hi> that's <hi>Vita deficiens;</hi> a life that is fraile and defectiue, next dore to death: and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Vita ſine vitâ,</hi> A life without life.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>life of Policy,</hi> that's <hi>Vita efficiens;</hi> a life that is operatiue and actiue: and is therefore <hi>Vita in vitâ,</hi> or, the life of life.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>life of Grace,</hi> that's <hi>Vita proficiens;</hi> a life that is ſtill proceeding in the workes of piety, and godlines: and is therefore <hi>Vita ſupra vitam,</hi> or, a life aboue life.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The <hi>life of Glory,</hi> that's <hi>vita perficiens;</hi> a life that is the accompliſhment and perfection of all happineſſe: and is therefore <hi>Vita poſt vitam,</hi> a life after life.</p>
            <p>By the firſt life, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivit ſibi,</hi> he liues to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>By the 2, <hi>Vivit reipublicae,</hi> he liue's to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth.</p>
            <p>By the 3, <hi>Viuit eccleſiae,</hi> he liue's to the Church.</p>
            <p>By the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivit D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he liue's for euer vnto God.</p>
            <p>Theſe 4 liues excell each other in <hi>degree</hi> of dignity. The later ſtill the better, and the laſt beſt of all. For, what's the life of nature in a King without policy? Or what's the life of policy, without grace? or what's the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16148:14"/>life of grace, without (if yet it could be without) the life of enſuing glory? For, what ſhall it profit a King to be King of the whole world, and to loſe the kingdome of heauen? or to be call'd a <hi>God</hi> heere on earth, if heereafter he ſhall proue but a damned <hi>Diuel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His three firſt liues, vnder God, are maintein'd and preſerued by the three profeſſions;
<hi>Diuinity, Law,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>natural life</hi> by <hi>Phyſicke;</hi> his <hi>politicke life</hi> by <hi>Law;</hi> and his <hi>spiritual life</hi> by <hi>Diuinity.</hi> Vpon which his <hi>ater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life</hi> (which is worth all the other three) will infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly follow.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe theſe three profeſſions of <hi>Diuinity, Law,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> are <hi>Filiae Academiarum,</hi> the <hi>three el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Daughters</hi> of the
<hi>Vniverſities;</hi> wiſely therefore, and worthily hath his Maieſtie that now is (for continuance and preſervation of our <hi>Vniverſities</hi>) not onely eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vnto vs thoſe royal <hi>Charters</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> which haue formerly been graunted vs by his <hi>Royal Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours</hi> in this kingdome: but further, now at this time,<note place="margin">But ſince that, there was a Mortmaine of 666 l 13 s 4 d: granted vs by his Maieſtie, Septembers 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Anno re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni Angl. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Scot. 48.</note> of his Princely goodnes he moſt gratiouſly propendeth to the graunting of a <hi>Mortmaine</hi> to our Vniverſity of Oxford for 500 l <hi>a yeare,</hi> more than wee had before. Which if we obteine, (as we hope, we ſhall.) then yee that are abundantly able, cannot ſay, that ye would giue more to our <hi>Vniuerſity,</hi> if it were capable: for it's capable of more, if you would giue it.</p>
            <p>But to proceede; I doubt not, but the life here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally pray'd for by the people, was the
<hi>natural,</hi> or <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral life</hi> of the King:<note place="margin">THE KINGS CORPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL LIFE here princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. 2 MOTIVES to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay for the Kings life.</note> for that's commonly all that the people either minde or care for, either in <hi>themſelues,</hi> or in <hi>their King.</hi> And for <hi>it</hi> to pray, they are ſtill put in mind, on the one ſide by the <hi>frailty</hi> of the Kings life: and that, not onely in reguard of the <hi>ſtuffe</hi> whereof hee is made, but alſo of thoſe many
<hi>dangers</hi> where with he is encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16148:15"/>On the other ſide, by the <hi>neceſſity</hi> thereof in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of themſelues, whoſe ſtate and life both depend's vpon his life.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt motiue</hi> then to pray for the Kings life,<note place="margin">1
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> LITAS, 1 Quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d materiam. Agapet. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is the
<hi>frailty</hi> of it. For a King (as <hi>Agapetus</hi> tell's the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi>) though he be <hi>like to God alone</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the power of his authority:</hi> yet is he <hi>like other men</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the ſubſtance and conſtitution of his body.</hi> And though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as in the Image of God:</hi> yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he is compacted but of the duſt of the earth.</hi> His golden head hath but feete of clay to ſupport it. Kings and ſubiects though there be an <hi>imparity</hi> in their <hi>birth,</hi> yet is there a <hi>parity</hi> in their
<hi>death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hodie rex, cras moritur;</hi> as it is Eccl. 10. <hi>To day a King, and to morrow a dead man.</hi> Yea, as ſure as a King is a man,<note place="margin">Platin. in vit. Pap. lo, 8.</note> ſo ſure is it, that he muſt dye-like a man.
<hi>Platina</hi> write's, that the <hi>Biſhops of Rome,</hi> who take themſelues to be Kings of all the Kings of the earth, and therefore play <hi>Rex</hi> in euery kingdome, vſed at their
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalling</hi> to ſit vpon the homelieſt kinde of ſtoole yee can thinke of (he call's it <hi>ſedem ſtercorariam</hi>) which yet was <hi>Cathedra,</hi> a ſeate fit enough for them. The inſtitution of which ceremony was to remember them, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their
<hi>Popedome,</hi> yet they are ſtill mortal, and ſubiect to the neceſſities of nature aſwell as other men; though it ſeeme's by their glorious, or rather blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſtyles of
<hi>Dominus Deus Papa, the Lord God the Pope, and the like,</hi> that they haue learn'd to make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it; as if then they began <hi>to eaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their mortality.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Quoad Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>la.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe: The <hi>frailty</hi> of a Kings life, as it is ſeene in the <hi>mouldering matter</hi> whereof hee is made: ſo-likewiſe in the <hi>multiplicity of dangers</hi> wherwith he is encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tered.<note place="margin">1 SPIRITV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AL enemies.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dangers</hi> both of <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and of <hi>Corporal enemies. Spiritual enemies</hi> to the natural life of a King are either
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16148:15"/>
               <hi>his owne ſins,</hi> or <hi>the ſins of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1 HIS OWN SINS.</note>1 <hi>His owne ſinnes;</hi> when he is not aſwell a <hi>Perſonal King</hi> over himſelfe, as a <hi>Polisike King</hi> over others; when he hath not aſwell <hi>Regnum rationis,</hi> a kingdome of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within him, to maiſter his owne paſſions, as <hi>Regnum nationis</hi> a kingdome of people without him, to rule as his owne ſubiects.<note place="margin">2 HIS PEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLES SINS.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 And as the Kings ſinnes, ſo are alſo the <hi>ſinnes of the people</hi> ſpirituall enemies to the naturall life of a King. The wiſeman tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s vs, Prov. 5. that <hi>ſin is bitter as worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 5.4.</note> I will add, that it hath one quality of wormewood more. For,
<hi>wormewood</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dioſcorides</hi>) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Dioſcor. l. 3. c. 26.</note> 
               <hi>offenſiue to ſtomach, and to head both,</hi> becauſe the fumes thereof ariſing from the ſtomach offend the head: and ſo oft times the King, who is the head, is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed and puniſh't for the ſins of the people.</p>
            <p>To what purpoſe then ſhall it be for you to cry, <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> Let the King liue, if the out-cry of your ſins ſound nothing but <hi>Moriatur Rex,</hi> Let the King dy? In vaine do your <hi>tongues</hi> pray for his life, if your <hi>ſins</hi> plot treaſon againſt his life. The Greeks haue <hi>one word</hi> that ſignifies <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> both: and thats <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and they haue <hi>another word</hi> that ſignifies <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Divel</hi> both: and that's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And tell me, I pray, are there not many that liue, as if they thought it all one, whither they go to <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> or to <hi>hell</hi> &amp; all one whither to <hi>God,</hi> or to the <hi>Divel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of <hi>lying</hi> and <hi>extortion</hi> (the two belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſins of your City) do not the ruffians, I ſay not of, but about this Citie, account <hi>drabbing</hi> and
<hi>dicing, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> and <hi>ſwilling,</hi> which indeed are <hi>foure Carnal</hi> &amp;
<hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal vices,</hi> to be their <hi>foure Cardinall</hi> and <hi>Moral virtues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſaid of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Ioh. 3. <hi>He muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and I muſt decreaſe:</hi> So,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.30.</note> if ye will haue the
<hi>Kings</hi> life to encreaſe, then muſt your ſins decreaſe. Your <hi>ſins</hi> muſt be ſhortned, that his <hi>dayes</hi> may be lengthned. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riantur
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16148:16"/>peccata, vs vivat Rex;</hi> Let your ſins dy, that your King may liue.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the death of ſin, is the life of the King; Let me add to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuat Rex, Vivat Pro-rex:</hi> Bleſſed be the godly and zealous care of him that is now his <hi>Maieſties <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy</hi> for the government of this honorable City, who ſo carefully &amp; painefully laboureth to purge thoſe more than <hi>Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in Stables</hi> where theſe ſins inhabit, which indeed will not be purged but with a ſtiffe ſircame.</p>
            <p>Yea, Let me alſo add one <hi>Vivat Rex</hi> more: <hi>Let that other King liue,</hi> a King but onely <hi>in name,</hi> ſaue that hee is <hi>indeed a King of Preachers;</hi> I meane the
<hi>R. Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of this <hi>Dioeceſe,</hi> than whom, I dare ſay, though (God be bleſſed) of late yeares, there haue riſen many, yet there never aroſe among you a truer
<hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> a man more zealous for the cauſe <hi>of the Lord of hoſts,</hi> and
<hi>of his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</hi> He as ready to cut downe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Gladio oris,</hi> with the ſword of his mouth, as is his Maieſties Liefetenent <hi>Ore gladij,</hi> with the edge of his ſword. Both reſolving with <hi>S. Ierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom. ep. 61.</note> that <hi>Ad tanta crimina patientem eſſe non oportet;</hi> Where ſuch ſins reigne, as reigne in and about this City, there it's a ſin for either <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> to be patient; every ſin being a <hi>ſworne-enemy</hi> to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural life of a King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 CORPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note>But beſides theſe <hi>ſpiritual enemies,</hi> there are alſo <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral enemies</hi> to the natural life of the King; ſons of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> that caſt off the yoake of obedience to their Liege King, and ſerue another King, even <hi>the Prince of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 12.31.</note> the
<hi>Divell,</hi> who is alſo <hi>their father:</hi> and yet are they not ſo wiſe, as to knowe
<hi>their owne father:</hi> like the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 8.33. V. 44.</note> ſaying. <hi>We are the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> when yet Chriſt tell's them, <hi>Ye are of your father the Divell.</hi> Theſe be they that haue <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex,</hi> God ſaue the King, in their <hi>mouth:</hi> but <hi>Vivat Papa,</hi> God ſaue the Pope, in their <hi>heart.</hi> They ſay, God ſaue the King, but it is but only <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16148:16"/>cauſa,</hi> for faſhions ſake: like as roagues do, when they are burnt in the hand: they ſay it, becauſe they muſt ſay it. With them <hi>Vivat Rex</hi> is but a
<hi>falſe cry;</hi> for even then when they ſay <hi>Vivat, God ſaue him;</hi> they rather wiſh, <hi>Moriatur, God haue him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aelius Sparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Antonin. Geta.</note> And as <hi>Baſſianus Caracalla</hi> ſaid of his owne Brother, whome hee had ſlaine; <hi>Sit Divus dum non ſit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivus,</hi> Let him (in God's name) be a <hi>Saint,</hi> ſo he be not a
<hi>Man:</hi> So, I wiſh we had not too-good cauſe to be perſwaded, that they could be content, to make out King <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iames,</hi> ſo they might vnmake him <hi>King Iames;</hi> to put him into their <hi>Kalender of Saints,</hi> ſo they might put him out of the <hi>Catalogue of Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Frenchmen</hi> haue a proverb; that <hi>Romam ad quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum ſanctum Petrum eunt, qui eum ante fores ſuas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent:</hi> There are that goe to ſeeke S. <hi>Peter</hi> at
<hi>Rome,</hi> when they haue him before their dores. And may it not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be ſaid of vs, that <hi>Antichriſtum Romae quaerimus, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mialimus?</hi> we ſeeke <hi>Antichriſt at Rome,</hi> but we cheriſh him here <hi>at home?</hi> Nay, I pray God we haue not ſome of
<hi>Solomon's Spiders</hi> among vs, that <hi>take hold with their hands, and are in Kings palaces,</hi> as it is Prov. 30. Some in <hi>Court</hi> aſwell as in <hi>Countrey,</hi> that are of the <hi>poyſoning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov 30.28.</note> and of the <hi>ſtabbing,</hi> and of the <hi>fiering Religion;</hi> who it were good they were ſoone ſwept downe with the
<hi>beſome of diſcipline,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 14.23.</note> leſt in the end they ſweepe downe all with the <hi>beſome of deſtruction!</hi> They haue learn'd of the
<hi>Seedeſmen</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> doctrine forged in the ſhop of that either
<hi>Tricoronis,</hi> or <hi>Tricornis Epiſcopus,</hi> that <hi>three-crown'd,</hi> or
<hi>three-horn'd Biſhop of Rome,</hi> that <hi>treaſon againſt a King not Catholike by their Copy, is no ſin againſt God.</hi> Theſe, theſe (beloued) the worſe <hi>Subiects</hi> they are to their Prince, the ſitter ſubiects are they for you that ſhalbee
<hi>Parliament-men</hi> to worke vpon. Buiſy not your heads in plotting and deviſing how to limit the poore <hi>Clergy</hi> to a ſtint of <hi>competency.</hi> For, where there is
<hi>Competency</hi> in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16148:17"/>the tongue, there is <hi>covetouſneſſe</hi> at leaſt, if not
<hi>irreligion</hi> in the heart. Study not, how ye may curb <hi>Chriſt in his Miniſters,</hi> but rather, how ye may ſubdue <hi>Antichriſt in his members.</hi> Remember (nay, I know ye cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) the <hi>children of Edom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> what they intended to haue acted at your laſt <hi>Parliament.</hi> To quit their en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſy ye ſhall do well to enact ſome ſtricter order againſt them now at your next <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſerved by <hi>Euſtathiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſtath. in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyl. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the people <hi>Arimas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Scythia</hi> are all borne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely with one
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The ground of which accident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e refer's to their <hi>winking with one ey</hi> when they ſhoot. For with much winking
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ayming, that ey wexed leſſe firſt in the fathers then in the ſons, and ſo in their ſons ſons for many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till at laſt they had wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kt it quite out, and ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued. I will not take vpon me to divine; but I pray God, we winke not ſo long at
<hi>Popery,</hi> till in the end we winke out the very EY of this our land, which is our Gratious
<hi>Soveraigne:</hi> &amp; the <hi>Ey</hi> of our ſoules too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is God's true
<hi>Religion.</hi> And my hearts deſire vnto God for this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is; that as his Maieſtie hath in this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed his <hi>Siſter-Queene,</hi> whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>after-fami</hi> ſhall never decay, ſo long as religion hath a tongue to ſpeake, that he hath in a manner extinguiſh'd thoſe <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatores, New Sectaries,</hi> or authors of innovation in Church diſcipline: So in this he would alſo ſurpaſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, even in weeding out thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eteratores,</hi> or crafty factors for the <hi>Old religion</hi> (as they call it) who haue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready trumpt dangers enough in his way, to arme him with expectation of nothing but inlaelicity &amp; miſchiefe at their hands. Away with all diſpenſation in matter of religion, which indeed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but nick-named a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A diſpenſation that is againſt right and reaſon (ſaith the <hi>Summiſt</hi> out of
<hi>Panormitan</hi>) is not to be called <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Angel: de Caſ: conſc.</note> 
               <hi>ſed Diſſipatie;</hi> a Diſpenſation, but a Diſſipation.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16148:17"/>
               <hi>Religio, à religando, Religion</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Auſtin</hi>) hath it's name of <hi>tying:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin. retrac. l. 1. c. 13. Lactant l. 4. c.
28. Hiſtor. tripart. l. 1. c. 7.</note> becauſe it's <hi>it</hi> that tyes and knitt's the hearts of the people, not only to <hi>God,</hi> but to their <hi>Prince</hi> too. And therfore
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour made Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which is <hi>the truth of Chriſt,</hi> to bee the touch-ſtone of the truth of his ſubiects loue to him. And becauſe hee would finde who were indeed his faithfull friends, hee cauſed proclamation to be made, that as many as would reneag the Chriſtian faith, they ſhould bee his friends, &amp; his Counſellours of eſtate; all the reſt muſt be packing. Wherevpon many of them revolting from the faith, in hope of preferment; others keeping the faith, but reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelues; the Emperour changed his decree, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thoſe onely in office which kept their ſaith to God, but expelling and amouing thoſe that denyed the faith, <hi>Ye</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that keepe not your faith with God, what hope can I haue, that ever ye ſhould proue faithfull ſubiects vnto me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such then being the condition, and <hi>frailty</hi> of Kings themſelues, that vncerteine it is whither they ſhall dy a <hi>dry,</hi> or a <hi>moiſt</hi> death; whither by the hand of God, or by the hands of men; it is but needfull that wee make his <hi>Maieſties Life</hi> our
<hi>Samuel,</hi> or our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.20. Plato l. quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam inſcribit <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> that is, <hi>that we aske it of God by prayer,</hi> that as his Maieſties reigne began with a preface of prayer (which indeed is the
<hi>beſt preface</hi> to every buſines) even a prayer of <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> God ſaue the King: So we ſhould ſtill continue our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for <hi>it,</hi> as we doe <hi>this day in publike,</hi> and as (I hope) we do <hi>every day in private;</hi> as being a thing which <hi>S. Paul</hi> would haue to be prayed for with <hi>an Inprimis,</hi> or firſt of all. 1. Tim. 2.</p>
            <p>And,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.</note> that I may ſet the keener edge vpon every one of you, for diſcharge of this ſo neceſſary a duty; Let it not grieue you (Beloued) if as
<hi>Chriſt's Sepulcher</hi> was made <hi>in a Garden,</hi> Io. 19. So in the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as I may ſay) of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16148:18"/>this day's ioy and triumph,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.41.</note> I do here build alſo <hi>your Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers:</hi> eſpecially, ſeeing we are now <hi>In Sepulchreto,</hi> in a Coemetery, or place of Sepulchers. <hi>Quòd ſi magna ruat quercus, trepidate myrica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Humfied. contr. monſt. prodit.</note> If the ax of death hew downe the great and mighty <hi>Oaks,</hi> ahlas what ſhall become of vs poore <hi>Shrubs?</hi> If death ſpare not the <hi>head</hi> it ſelfe, how ſhould the <hi>members</hi> hope to eſcape? Wherefore as <hi>Zip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porah circumciſed her ſon with a ſharp ſtone,</hi> Ex. 4.<note place="margin">Ex. 4.25</note> So let all of vs circumciſe our hearts with remembrance of the
<hi>graue ſtone,</hi> from which none, no, not Princes themſelues can plead exemption.</p>
            <p>There are of you who either haue, or may haue your chambers as gorgeouſly and as ſumptuouſly bedeckt, as was that higheſt dining chamber (in <hi>Pliny</hi>) which ranne round about continually like the heavens;<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; in the roofe of it were curiouſly wrought, the Sun, the Moone, &amp; the Starres. And yet when ye haue made you ſuch a <hi>Heauen</hi> here on <hi>earth,</hi> dy ye muſt: <hi>Earth</hi> muſt, and will to <hi>Earth.</hi> But ahlas (Beloued) this is it that deceiues vs: we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient either to heare, or thinke of death till it come. Whence it is, that though we haue <hi>Tot ſpectacula, tot specula,</hi> ſo many ſpectacles, and ſo many looking-glaſſes of mortality before our eyes, yet are wee like to thoſe that are bitten with mad dogs, <hi>Qui ſespſos non noſcunt in speculo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gerſon.</note> who knowe not themſelues in a glaſſe.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſecond motiue</hi> to the people to pray for the Kings life,<note place="margin">1 NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITAS.</note> is the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of it in reguard of themſelues. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex, vt Vivat Regnum.</hi> Let the King liue, that his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may liue; for the Kings life is the life of the whole Kingdome. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the very word in my text for a King) is ſo call'd, becauſe he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the foundation of the people:<note place="margin">Greg. Mor. 9. l. c. 10. Sap. 6.24.</note> according to which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the wiſe man ſaith, Sap. 6. that a wiſe King is <hi>Stabilimentum populi,</hi> the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, or ſtay, or ſtaffe of his people. And becauſe a King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16148:18"/>is <hi>Perſona publica,</hi> not a private, but a publike perſon; hence is it, that his ſtyle, is, <hi>Mandamus &amp; Volumus,</hi> in the plural, <hi>We</hi> will and command. So that when the people pray for the King, they do indeed in effect pray for them ſelues. <hi>Accidentia non ſunt entia, niſi quia ſunt entis,</hi> (ſaith the Philoſopher. Met. l. 7.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. Met. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>) Accidents haue no being of themſelues, but onely as they are inhaerent in a ſubſtance which hath a ſelfe-being. And ſurely, ſo may the people ſay to their King, <hi>Quòd vivo &amp; valeo, ſi valeo, tuum eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that both their being, and their well-being depend's vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. As therefore one can wiſh a covetous man no greater miſchiefe than a <hi>long life,</hi> becauſe he is the cauſe of his owne ill: No more can the people wiſh themſelues any greater good than the
<hi>life of the King,</hi> becauſe he is the cauſe of all their weale. A King then being
<hi>Totum populi,</hi> the total-ſumme (as I may ſay) of all the peoples welfare, good reaſon that <hi>Totus populus,</hi> not ſome, but <hi>all</hi> the people ſhould iointly pray for
<hi>His</hi> welfare; that both <hi>Vox &amp; Votum,</hi> their voice, and their wiſh,
<hi>Chordula &amp; Cor,</hi> their tongue-ſtring, and their heart-ſtring, <hi>Clamor &amp; Amor,</hi> their loude ſhoute, and their loue ſhould ſound in an vniſon, to make vp this ſweet conſort of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Rex,</hi> God ſaue the King: that they ſhould doe, as the people doe in my text, <hi>Clamare,</hi> as it were rend and teare the very clouds with the cry and ſhoute of their prayers, that they may pull downe a bleſſing of long life vpon the head of the King: crying both <hi>vnâ voce,</hi> with one voice, that they haue <hi>Vnum Regem,</hi> but one King, &amp; <hi>vivâ voce</hi> with a loude, on liuely voice, that they may haue
<hi>Vivum Regem,</hi> a huing King; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far of <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> as it is a ſupplication.</p>
            <p>It's now more than time I ſhould ſpeake of it, as it is an <hi>Acclamation,</hi> or a voice of ioy and thankſgiuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: and therefore now this <hi>ſecond acception</hi> ſhall onely ſerue me for <hi>Application</hi> to the day. <hi>Vivat Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16148:19"/>
               <note place="margin">PART 2. ACCLAMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, fereuing for AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLICATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON.</note>The ioints and paſſages of our ioy and thankſgiuing may be <hi>three.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That we haue <hi>Regem,</hi> a King.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> That we haue <hi>Talem,</hi> ſuch a King, who for his match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Graces and virtues, may more truely bee call'd a <hi>None-ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 118.24.</note>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. That <hi>this</hi> is the day, <hi>Quem fecit Dominus,</hi> which the Lord hath made; nay rather, <hi>In quo factus aſt Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Wherein <hi>King Iames</hi> was made our <hi>Lord.</hi> It is the day of our reioycing for his Crowne, and ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be the Crowne of our reioycing.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">REIOICE, that we haue 1 REGEM.</note>1 Firſt then reioice we that we haue a King. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ixit Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina,</hi> we had a Queene, who had ſhee liued, wee ſhould haue thought, we had had no need of <hi>King Iames:</hi> But now <hi>Vivit Rex,</hi> we haue a King, and while <hi>He</hi> liues, we haue cauſe to ſay, we haue no need of <hi>Queene Elſabeth. Both</hi> of them ſo incomparably excellent, that it muſt be the commendation of <hi>both,</hi> that <hi>either</hi> of them was like <hi>the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. epiſt. l. 3. ep. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoch.</note>She was a <hi>Queene,</hi> of whom we might truly ſay as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaid of that <hi>Roman Paula; Vnius contempſit glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vrbis, totius orbis opinione celebratur,</hi> She contemn'd the glory of <hi>one City,</hi> her name is pretious throughout the <hi>whole World.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eurip. Hecub.</note> Or rather, as <hi>Euripides</hi> ſaid of <hi>Polyxena,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>ſetting aſide her mortality, ſhe was a Goddeſſe here on earth.</hi> Inſomuch that Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians did even bluſh at their old rule of <hi>Maſculinum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius eſt Faminino.</hi> The maſculine gender is more worthy than the faeminine; till <hi>King Iames,</hi> as on this day, came as our <hi>Dayes-man,</hi> to arbitrate the matter, and to vindicate the credit of <hi>His ſexe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was not without cauſe, that during the time of that ſhort <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> or enter-ſpace of reigne betweene the death of that bleſſed <hi>Queene,</hi> and the entring of our bleſſed <hi>King</hi> to this kingdome,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 7.5.</note> 
               <hi>our</hi> hearts <hi>did melt like
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16148:19"/>water,</hi> as did the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelties.</hi> For, what euils had we not then iuſt cauſe to expect? But, when the wine of all our comfort failed vs, when the pitchers and veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of our hearts ouerflowed with the water of ſorow and compunction; then did God, euen the God of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> who is a moſt praeſent and extemporary helpe in the needfull time of trouble, of his owne free bounty, and mercy, turne our water, (our ſalt water) into wine. Then did our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or King grow vp as it were in an inſtant, like the
<hi>herbe Baſil,</hi> call'd <hi>Baſilica,</hi> or <hi>Regia berba,</hi> which by ſome is alſo call'd <hi>Ocymum,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>celerity</hi> and ſodainnes of it's growth; <hi>His title</hi> (contrary to the hope of our foes, and feare of our friends) taking firme and peaceable footing in our land, before <hi>his perſon:</hi> and that,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the effuſion or ſhedding of any one drop either of
<hi>bloud;</hi> or of <hi>ſweate.</hi> So that, as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Laban,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30.30.</note> Gen. 30, <hi>Benedixit tibi Dominus ad introitum meum,</hi> The Lord hath bleſſed thee by my comming; So may our <hi>Iacob</hi> ſay to this land of ours. And in a better ſenſe may this Land of ours ſing, SOL RE ME FA: that is, <hi>SOLus REx ME FAcit,</hi> It's the King onely (vnder God) that mak'sane; than could one of the <hi>Popes,</hi> of whom <hi>the ſame ſong</hi> was ſet vp as a <hi>Paſquil</hi> in <hi>Rome;</hi> meaning, that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> had made him <hi>Pope,</hi> by giuing a <hi>Spaniſh fig</hi> to ſome of his praedeceſſors in that See.</p>
            <p>And ſo (as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes of the ſorowes &amp; ioyes of the righteous,)
<hi>Tristitia noſtra habet Quaſi;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſt. in Pſ. 48.</note> 
               <hi>ſed Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia noſtra non habet Quaſi,</hi> Our ſorow for <hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabeth</hi> was but
<hi>as it were</hi> ſorow; but our ioy for <hi>King Iames</hi> is ioy <hi>indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 NOT A PLVRALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY.</note>
               <hi>Ioy indeede,</hi> and <hi>greate ioy;</hi> that we haue not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>plurality</hi> of Kings. For Kings (they ſay) are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of copartners; and kingdomes (I am ſure) are as impatient of them, as Kings themſelues. The world at
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16148:20"/>ſome times can hardly endure the <hi>heate</hi> but of one Sun; but certes, if there were two Sunnes, they would quite burne it vp.</p>
            <p>It's an old, and for the moſt part a true rule in <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy,</hi> that hee that hath but
<hi>one ſervant,</hi> hath <hi>a whole ſervant;</hi> he that hath <hi>two,</hi> hath but
<hi>halfe a ſervant;</hi> but he that hath <hi>three,</hi> hath <hi>never a ſervant.</hi> And no leſſe true is it in <hi>Policy,</hi> of Kings who are <hi>Servipublici,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Servants; (for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A ruler,<note place="margin">Max. Tyr. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. 20.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ub fin.</note> or a King (ſaith <hi>Max. Tyrius</hi>) is ſeruant to many Maſters.) <hi>One King, a whole King; two Kings, halfe a King; three Kings,</hi> and <hi>never a King.</hi> In 1 Macch. 1: we reade,<note place="margin">1. Macch.
1.10.</note> that after the death of <hi>King Alexander,</hi> his ſeruants ſhared his kingdome among them, and ſo the <hi>Macedonians</hi> in ſteed of <hi>one</hi> King, had <hi>many</hi> Kings: But ſee what followes in the very next words; <hi>Et multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata ſunt mala in terrâ,</hi> and much wickednes encreaſed in the land.</p>
            <p>O how happy then we, that haue not <hi>Regem vnum in pluribus,</hi> a King that is but one among many, but <hi>Plures in vno,</hi> many Kings in one! The King of <hi>England,</hi> the King of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> the King of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> all <hi>foure</hi> Kings in our <hi>one</hi> King. So that he is not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. nom. l. 4.</note> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Vnus.</hi> but
<hi>vnitivus; one</hi> King, or a <hi>ſingular</hi> King, but a King <hi>that makes one</hi> of many.</p>
            <p>Yea the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nations, which before were <hi>diuided</hi> no leſſe in <hi>heart,</hi> than in <hi>kingdome,</hi> hath hee now ſo <hi>concorporated,</hi> or rather <hi>coanimated</hi> into <hi>one,</hi> that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is fulfilled what was promiſed as a bleſſing to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 37.22.</note> Ezech. 37:
<hi>I will make them one people in the land vpon the mountaines of Iſrael, &amp; one King ſhalbe King to them all, &amp; they ſhalbe no more two peoples, neither bee divided any more henceforth into two kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then is matter of <hi>greate ioy,</hi> that we haue not a <hi>plurality</hi> of Kings, but
<hi>one ſole, entire,</hi> and <hi>abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16148:20"/>
               <note place="margin">2 NOT A NVLLITY.</note>And yet, behold matter of <hi>greater ioy</hi> than this; That as wee are freed from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>plurality</hi> of Kings, which is <hi>bad,</hi> ſo likewiſe from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Nullity,</hi> which is
<hi>worſe.</hi> It was a greate puniſhment to them, when they had <hi>no Smith in Iſrael,</hi> 1 Sam. 13: but far greater,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.19. Iudg. 17.6.</note> when they had <hi>no King in Iſrael,</hi> Iudg. 17: for then (as it preſently followes) <hi>Euery man did that which was good in his owne eyes;</hi> that is, when there was <hi>no</hi> King, then would <hi>euery man</hi> be a King, to do what he luſted.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>ataxy,</hi> or diſorder, becauſe it vſually follow's v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>anarchy,</hi> or lack of a King, it is therefore noted of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that they were wont for fiue dayes after their Kings death, to let their Lawes ſleep without exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and to let euery man do what he pleaſed, that in thoſe fiue dayes men ſeeing the rage and tyranny of ſin and iniuſtice for lack of gouernment, might more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly obey their King euer after.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 THAT we haue TALEM.</note>But, that which is indeede matter of our
<hi>greateſt ioy,</hi> is, that wee haue not onely <hi>Regem,</hi> a King, but <hi>Talem,</hi> ſuch a King; if yet I may call him <hi>Talem,</hi> who hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a <hi>Qualem</hi> to aequal him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hieron, ad Pammachan prolog. l. 2. in Hoſe.</note>Of whom may be verified that which <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ierom</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of <hi>Cato,</hi> out of <hi>Liuy;</hi> that <hi>Eius gloriae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> profuit quiſquam laudando, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vituperando quiſquam nocuit, cum vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſummis praditi ingenijs fecerint,</hi> though <hi>M. Cicero,</hi> &amp; <hi>C Caſar</hi> (<hi>both</hi> of excellent parts) writ, the one in his <hi>praiſe,</hi> the other in his <hi>dispraiſe,</hi> yet neither did the praiſe of the one <hi>add</hi> any thing to him, nor the diſpraiſe of the other <hi>detract</hi> any thing from him.</p>
            <p>For, what can all thoſe <hi>black-tongued Parrets,</hi> or foule-mouth'd railers of
<hi>Rome,</hi> for their bitterneſſe like thoſe <hi>blacke ſtyes</hi> (in
<hi>Theophrastus</hi>) bred <hi>ex abſynthij ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophraſt. de cauſ. Plant. l. 4. c. 16.</note> of the ſeede o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Worme-wood: I ſay, what can all of them with all their <hi>Caninae facundia,</hi> or barking clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, detract from his Maieſtie? Or, what can the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16148:21"/>beſt <hi>Orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> among thoſe that are his beſt ſubiects, add vnto him?</p>
            <p>It was the opinion of a greate <hi>Orator,</hi> (how ſound, I now diſpute not) that
<hi>Kings would,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſocr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>for the moſt part, be better than private men, St Reges electio, non ſucceſſio faceres,</hi> if they were made by election, not by ſucceſſion. But, ſay our King had not come vnto vs by <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> as <hi>He</hi> did, but that our ſelues had beene to make the <hi>election,</hi> I would faine know, where wee could haue made ſuch another choice.</p>
            <p>For, is not <hi>King Iames</hi> like the <hi>Adamant, Gemma Principum, &amp; Princeps Gemmarum,</hi> the Gemme of Princes, and the Prince of Gemmes; euen the moſt pretious
<hi>Gemme</hi> in the <hi>Ring</hi> of this round World? A Gemme, all whoſe brightneſſe and beauty is from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; A Gemme, which is ſomuch the more reſplendent, becauſe it is ſet in gold; and a Gemme, whoſe far and neare-ſhining <hi>virtues</hi> ſhall hereafter be as ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Gemmes in his caeleſtial <hi>Diademe?</hi> Is he not (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Sun</hi>) <hi>Oculus mundi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. he xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emd, 3. c.
1.</note> the <hi>Ey</hi> of the whole world? nay, hee on whom the eyes of the whole world are caſt? &amp; <hi>Iucunditas diei,</hi> the <hi>Ioy</hi> not of <hi>this</hi> day onely, but of all the dayes of our life? and <hi>Naturae Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> the very <hi>grace</hi> and ornament of Nature?</p>
            <p>A King deſcended of ſo many noble and royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitours,<note place="margin">1 NOBILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY.</note> that if hee had but one drop of bloud-royal from euery one of them, it were almoſt bloud enough for his whole body. And, as if hee had beene borne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee a King, he began both his <hi>Life,</hi> and his <hi>Reigne</hi> at once; and therefore hee came into our Land with a Crowne vpon his head, <hi>Non tam factus, quàm natus,</hi> we rather <hi>found,</hi> than <hi>founded</hi> him a King.</p>
            <p>And (which is not ſomuch the <hi>fruite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 VIRTVES.</note> as the
<hi>roote</hi> of his <hi>Nobility</hi>) a King ſo <hi>virtuous,</hi> that he is like the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers <hi>Medium morale,</hi> or moral meane, in which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16148:21"/>they place <hi>onely virtue,</hi> and no vice.</p>
            <p>And (which is the fruite of his <hi>virtue</hi>) a King ſo <hi>peaceable,</hi> that as
<hi>Pliny</hi> write's of the bird <hi>Halcyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 PEACE. Plin. 1. 2. c.
47.</note> or the <hi>Kings-fiſher,</hi> that <hi>while ſhee makes her neſt in the ſea, the ſea is becalmed;</hi> ſo ſince He hath neſtled himſelfe in this our kingdome, (which we fear'd at the death of that Noble Queene, would haue proued a <hi>Sea</hi> of troubles) wee haue had none but <hi>Halcyontan</hi> dayes, dayes of calme, and of peace.</p>
            <p>And (which is the fruite of <hi>peace</hi>) a King ſo <hi>learned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 IEAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING.</note> that whither he <hi>ſpeake,</hi> he ſpeak's ſo elegantly, that like another
<hi>Palamedes,</hi> he may well be call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Nightingale of the Muſes;</hi> or whither hee <hi>write,</hi> write's ſo inſpiredly, ſo diuinely, as if hee wrote with a pen out of the wing of that ſacred Doue, the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I may ſay, for the vniverſality of his knowledge, that we haue a <hi>Head,</hi> not inferiour to that <hi>braſen-Head</hi> made by <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> and placed in his Study; which (if we will beleeue <hi>Toſtat</hi>) could readily anſwere <hi>Ad omnia quaſita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Toſtat. in lib. Numer. c. 21. quaſt. 19.</note> to whatſoeuer quaeſtions were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of it. Since the beginning of the world was it euer ſeene, that any King but He, turn'd <hi>Cathedram Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> his Chaire of Eſtate, <hi>In Cathedram Regentis,</hi> into a Moderator's Chaire, and publikely moderated in our <hi>Vniuerſity Acts?</hi> and that, with ſuch applauſe, as was able to turne Envy it ſelfe into Admiration?</p>
            <p>And (which is the fruite of his <hi>learning</hi>) a King ſo <hi>religious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON. Polychtonic</note> that as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bare clay vpon his owne ſhoulders to the building of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter's</hi> Church; ſo hath his Maieſtie in his owne Perſon, and with his owne pen, manfully maintein'd the cauſe of Religion; ſo manfully that as the Adverſaries of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue juſt cauſe to be more afraid of his <hi>pen,</hi> than of his <hi>launce;</hi> So hath hee iuſt cauſe to be more afraid of then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16148:22"/>
               <hi>launce,</hi> their <hi>ſtab,</hi> their <hi>gun-powder,</hi> than their
<hi>pen.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any King, in this reſpect, ſo rightly term'd <hi>Defendour of the Faith,</hi> as He.</p>
            <p>And (which is the fruite of his <hi>Religion</hi>) a King no leſſe <hi>deare vnto God,</hi> than is <hi>God to him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 DELIVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCES.</note> ſo that he may well be call'd <hi>Amicus Dei,</hi> the friend of God, as was <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iac.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23.</note> Iac. 2. As hee hath beene God's
<hi>Buckler</hi> to defend his Religion <hi>In ſalute veritatis,</hi> in the ſafety of truth; ſo hath God beene to him what he was to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Gen.<note place="margin">Gen.
15.1.</note> 15: <hi>his buckler</hi> to defend him <hi>In veritate ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis,</hi> in the truth of ſafety, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeak's, Pſal.<note place="margin">Pſal.
68.17.</note> 68. And as the King hath ſhew'd himſelfe to bee <hi>Iacobum Dei, Iames</hi> by the grace of God in the one; ſo hath God ſhew'd himſelfe to bee <hi>Deum Iacobi,</hi> the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious God of King <hi>Iames</hi> in the other; by his many (no leſſe mighty, than miraculous) deliuerances of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, witneſſing to all the world, that his
<hi>will</hi> concurr's with the peoples <hi>wiſh</hi> of <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> God ſaue the King; and that if euer <hi>Vox populs,</hi> the voice of the people, were (according to the Proverb) <hi>Vox Dei,</hi> the voice of God; then was it at the promulgation of <hi>King Iames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly (which is the fruite of Gods <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>fauour</hi> both to
<hi>him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 FRVIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLNES.</note> and <hi>vs,</hi> and the pledge of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſſe) a King ſo <hi>fruitfull</hi> both in <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and in <hi>his Iſſue,</hi> that though He be <hi>Optimus,</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we had, yet (bleſſed be God for it) wee cannot ſay, as one ſaid of <hi>Brutus,</hi> that He is
<hi>Vltimus,</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> of worth that euer we are likely to haue.</p>
            <p>For, though our iniquities tooke from our bead a right hopeful Prince, whoſe life was as ſweete, as it was ſhort, and (were it not that God hath otherwiſe ſo rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided for vs) to bee deplored not with teares of water from our eyes, but with ſtreames of bloud from our hearts: yet (thankes be to God) there wants not as hopeful a ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;<note place="margin">Virg. Aen. 6.</note> — <hi>Prime avulſo non deficit alter Aureus,</hi>—
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16148:22"/>as the Poe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpake of thoſe <hi>golden bought,</hi> No ſooner is one
<hi>ſhred off,</hi> but another <hi>ſhoot</hi>'s <hi>out.</hi> For, of thoſe <hi>two pretious Pearles</hi> which yet ſurviue, (as doth alſo <hi>the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of them our gratious
<hi>Queene Anne,</hi> who is not yet ſo <hi>ſuperannated,</hi> but that, by Gods grace, ſhe may bee a ioyfull Mother of many more) is not one of them ſince become a timely and teeming
<hi>Mother?</hi> who (not long ſince) ſent a more ioyous and welcome newes to out King, than
<hi>Berſabe</hi> did to <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2 Sam. 11: ſaying,<note place="margin">2 Sam.
11.5.</note> not as ſhe did, <hi>Concepi,</hi> I am with child, but <hi>Pepere,</hi> I haue a child. I pray God there may neuer come worſe newes to <hi>England!</hi> and becauſe better cannot come, that many ſuch meſſages She may liue to ſend!</p>
            <p>And now, after all this, tell me, if ye might, would ye haue choſen <hi>another</hi> King? or if yee would, could yee haue choſen <hi>ſuch another?</hi> Doth not our King as much excell other Kings in goodneſſe, as the <hi>Whale</hi> in the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Sea exceeds the
<hi>Dolphin</hi> in bigneſſe?</p>
            <q>Quantùm Delphinis Balaena Britannica maior?</q>
            <p>Beloued, if honor be due vnto our King, as he is <hi>a King,</hi> then much more, as he <hi>is ſuch a King.</hi> And if thankes be due vnto God for <hi>giuing vs a King,</hi> then much more, for <hi>giuing vs ſuch a King.</hi> I haue therefore ſomuch honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and magnified the King vnto you, that ye might ſo much the more honor Him, whom GOD hath ſo highly honored with all the moſt glorious graces of a King; as alſo that yee might ſomuch the more magnify God for Him, who hath ſo magnified his mercies towards you in Him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 THIS DAY.</note>And becauſe (of all others) <hi>this</hi> is the day when this inaeſtimable bleſſing was beſtowed on vs, therefore doth <hi>this</hi> day aboue others, chalenge a due and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reguard of it at our hands; That, as on this day God bleſſed our King with ſuch a people, vs his people with ſuch a King; ſo on this day both
<hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16148:23"/>head</hi> and <hi>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> as <hi>Eſar</hi> cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s them, chap. 9:<note place="margin">Eſa 9.14.</note> ſhould offer vp the <hi>ſacrifice of thank
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing</hi> vnto God; euen as it was commanded in the Old Law,<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.9.</note>
               <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>put cum Cauda.</hi> that both head and ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le ſhould bee ſacrificed together; and that both of vs ſhould render <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>subilaeo, iubilum,</hi> the voice of ioy and <hi>iubilation</hi> for our <hi>Iubile</hi> or deliuerance:
<hi>Our del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erance</hi> from thoſe bloudy and dangerous vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares, which, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on this day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both of vs ſomuch feared, but eſpecially for <hi>our deliuerance</hi> from the tyranny of
<hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which we (his people) ſomuch abhorted.</p>
            <p>I may call it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.12.</note> in <hi>Dav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a's</hi> phraſe, Pſal. 64. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oronam anni benignitatis Dei,</hi> the crowne of the yeare of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God. or <hi>the day</hi> wherein the Lord crown'd our yeares with his goodneſſe. For, as according to our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> computation it is the <hi>Vig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> or <hi>Eue</hi> to a <hi>ſecond New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares day,</hi> becauſe from it our <hi>accounts</hi> and <hi>acts</hi> reckon the <hi>new yeare:</hi> ſo was it <hi>the beginning</hi> of the <hi>acceptable yeare of the Lord,</hi> even of a
<hi>ſpiritual Iubile</hi> vnto vs. <hi>Dies vere Evangelicus,</hi> a day of glad tidings indeed: For in it was brought vnto vs <hi>Evangelium Evangelij,</hi> the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the glad tidings of the Goſpel: or (if ye will) <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uteronomium Evangelij,</hi> the Deuteronomy, or repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Goſpel. It's the day of the <hi>Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation</hi> of the <hi>conception</hi> of our bleſſed <hi>King,</hi> in the <hi>wombe</hi> of this our <hi>Land:</hi> and it's the <hi>Prodromus,</hi> or fore-runner to the <hi>Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation</hi> of the <hi>conception</hi> of our bleſſed <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> in the
<hi>womb</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Virgin. This</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our <hi>temporal redemption; That</hi> the beginning of our <hi>ſpiritual redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is reported of the <hi>Duke of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſ.</note> that hee doth <hi>Quotannts cum mars sponſalia ſolenniter contrahere,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare ſolemnely contract, and eſpouſe himſelfe to the Sea; and in token of that contract, hee doth <hi>Annulum porrigere,</hi> as it were <hi>wed</hi> himſelfe to the <hi>Sea</hi> with a <hi>Ring:</hi> ſignifying thereby, that his chiefe care and ſtudy ſhalbe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16148:23"/>in pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing
<hi>Ships<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ch are the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ete mumtion and defenſe of his D mimons:</p>
            <p>So let vs (Beloued) in like manner <hi>yeare be yeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ennize, and (what in vs is)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e the rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of <hi>the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey:</hi> and <hi>toties quoties,</hi> even as oft as it ſhall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turne, let vs make
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it were a <hi>New League,</hi> or
<hi>Eſpoulais</hi> with it: and in token of that league. let vs ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill other the <hi>Ring</hi> (as I may ca l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t) of this <hi>anniverſary,</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution</hi> of our <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> vnto God, to remame as a ſure <hi>loue-token,</hi> or <hi>covenant</hi> betwixt <hi>vs</hi> and <hi>our King,</hi> as immoueable. as inuiolable, as is the <hi>covenant of day and night.</hi> And, as
<hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Numb. 13.<note place="margin">Num. 13.3.</note> So ſay I vnto you, <hi>Remember this day:</hi> which while I am now remembring, I <hi>am</hi> even in an <hi>Extaſy,</hi> and cannot tell how to ſtyle it; whither the <hi>spring of our ioy;</hi> or <hi>the ioy of our spring;</hi> or the <hi>day spring of our light;</hi> or the <hi>wel-spring of our wealth;</hi> or the <hi>head-ſpring,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſpring-head of all our happineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, let me not ſtreighten our <hi>thanksgiuing</hi> to <hi>this day</hi> onely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.2.</note> but rath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as
<hi>David</hi> will's vs, Pſ. 95. <hi>Annunti-te de die in diem ſalutare eius,</hi> Let every day be the <hi>Feast</hi> of this bleſſed <hi>Annuntiation</hi> of our ſalvation. Let vs not onely keepe this day <hi>feſtival</hi> vnto the King, but let vs ſay with the Prophet
<hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 75 <hi>Reliquiae cogitationis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em feſtum agent tibi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.10.</note> The remainder of my thoughts ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l keepe <hi>holy day</hi> vnto thee. And as we began the <hi>firſt day;</hi> ſo let vs both <hi>beginne, and end all the daies</hi> of His reigne, with <hi>Vivat Rex:</hi> Let that be both our <hi>Mattens,</hi> and our <hi>Evenſong, every day.</hi> And as I
<hi>began</hi> my diſcourſe, ſo will I <hi>end,</hi> with <hi>Vivat Rex;</hi> and let <hi>all the people</hi> ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat:</hi> and let <hi>God</hi> put to his <hi>Fiat,</hi> that ſo it may be. <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VIVAT REX.</hi> LET THE KING LIVE.</p>
            <p>Let Him liue the <hi>life of Nature,</hi> maugre the beards &amp; treacheries of all His malicious and bloud-thirſty ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16148:24"/>who weepe, becauſe they ſee nothing worthy the weeping at.</p>
            <p>Let Him liue <hi>the life of Policy,</hi> by a due execution of all Princely duties, and ſo liue in the hearts and loue of his Subiects, which ſhould hee loſe, Hee ſhould
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther <hi>breath,</hi> than <hi>liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let Him liue <hi>the life of Grace,</hi> by a fervent loue of thy truth, that thy mercy and truth may embrace Him on every ſide; and that thou maiſt make an everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Him,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.3.</note> even <hi>the ſure mercies of David.</hi> Laſtly, after theſe <hi>three liues</hi> ended here on earth, let him for <hi>ever liue and reigne</hi> with thee in the <hi>life and kingdome of glory;</hi> who liueſt and reigneſt world without ende. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16148:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
